Guide to the United States Steel Corporation National-Duquesne Works Records, 1890-1985 AIS.1991.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United States Steel Corporation National-Duquesne Works Records
1890-1985
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United States Steel Corporation
AIS.1991.06
379 Linear Feet (303 boxes, 98 reels of microfilm, 23 ledgers, 5 binders, 2 oversized items, 22 video cassettes)
The National Tube Works was started by John H. and Harvey K. Flagler in East Boston, Massachusetts in 1868 and in 1871 they opened a mill in McKeesport, Pa. The company become a subsidiary of U.S. Steel in 1900 and merged with the Duquesne Works in the late 1960s before closing in 1987. The USX National-Duquesne Works records offer an unusual richness of documentation on the workforce at a major steel producer which was in operation for over a century. Digital reproductions of selected material are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of selected material are available online.
History
John H. and Harvey K. Flagler established the National Tube Works Company in East Boston, Massachusetts in 1868. In 1872, the Flaglers opened a mill in McKeesport, Pennsylvania, in order to be closer to the Pennsylvania oil fields which used their piping. A few months after the mill opened, it was destroyed by a fire. It was rapidly rebuilt, and, by 1890, the plant employed approximately 3,000. In 1891, the company purchased the Monongahela Furnace Company, allowing them to control the production of their pipes from ore to finished product. Subsequently, they built a steel mill so that they could use steel for tubing. In 1899, the National Tube Company was formed as a consolidation of the majority of pipe and tube mills in the United States. The company became a subsidiary of U.S. Steel in 1900, allowing the McKeesport plan t to expand to over 150 acres. In 1937, production and maintenance workers won union recognition and bargaining rights as Local 1408 of the Steelworkers Organizing Committee (later United Steelworkers of America). Salaried workers formed a separate USWA local as did other categories of employees. In the early 1940s, the works became part of the National Tube Division of U.S. Steel in a realignment designed to help rationalize war-related production. In the late 1960s, as demand for their products declined, U.S. Steel merged the National Tube Works with the Duquesne Works to form the National-Duquesne Works. Both plants were downsized in the early 1980s, and the Duquesne plant closed in 1985. National Works was then merged with the U.S. Steel Mon-Valley Works and continued to produce tubing until the plant closed its doors for good in 1987.
Scope and Content Notes
The USX National-Duquesne Works Records offer an unusual richness of documentation on the workforce at a major steel producer in operation for over a century. Inactive pension files reflect job and wage progressions of native and immigrant workers, as far back as the 1870s. Statistical breakdowns of mill accidents according to occupation, nationality, department, severity, cause, and part of the body affected are present for the 1912-1918 period, while individual case files as well as periodical statistical reports of injuries commence in 1930. An extensive set of grievance records documents shop floor relations from the 1930s to 1980s.
Also of interest are the more than 12,000 employee National Defense cards from the 1940s and a smaller set for the 1950s. Approximately 30% of the early 1940s card series contain thumbnail photographs of the employees. Ledgers dating from 1941 to 1966 recorded citizenship verification information and address listings. Management and clerical personnel are also documented in the collection in various ways.
There are binders which contain photographs of supervisory personnel at National Works (1950s) and Duquesne Works (1980), and employment records for foremen and other salaried workers. Videotape safety programs, safety posters and numerous primarily safety-related 35 mm slides, document the company approach to accident prevention, while minutes of company-union safety meetings, along with grievance records, show the points of contention and correspondence in the approach to plant safety. Corporate public relations films are also of interest.
A microfilmed set of company-filmed employment records provides additional demographic information on employees, while some other employment related files, including some pension files, which were water damaged when accessioned, have been microfilmed by the University Library System for the Archives. Finally, company subject files on strikes and work stoppages from the post-union period are significant in their detail, while some manuscript narratives from pre-union period strikes at National Tube (1891, 1904, and 1919) are colored by their author's management perspective.
Arrangement
Series I. History of National Tube Works
Series II. Employee Relations
Series III. Accounting
Series IV. Union Check Offs
Series V. Ledgers
Series VI. Presentations
Series VII. Photographs, 1943-1957
Access Restrictions
Medical and personnel records in the collection (Boxes 77-90, 208-232 and Reel 65, 67-93) are restricted for 75 years from date of creation. Until this restriction is lifted, researchers must sign a confidentiality agreement if wishing to access this information. Please contact the Archives Service Center for more information.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Regional Industrial Development Corporation, 1991.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Microfilm is mostly 16mm.
Previous Citation
United States Steel Corporation National-Duquesne Works Records, 1890-1985, AIS.1991.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Records, 1916-1980 and U.S. Steel Corp. National-Duquesne Works Records, 1890-1985, uelab199106, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Originals
Most of the material that has been microfilmed by ULS was destroyed due to prior damage.
Related Material
United States Steel Corporation Duquesne Works, Industrial Relations Department Records, 1904-1980, AIS.1987.03, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Separated Material
Microfilm made by USX and of documents that were too damaged to be salvaged can be found in the Reading Room at the Archives Service Center.
Ledgers from the National-Duquesne Works are located in Range 1/12/2.
Oversize posters are located in map-case 3 drawer 12.
McKeesport (Pa.); Business and Industry; Labor; Iron and steel workers; Steel industry and trade -- United States; McShane, William J.; United States Steel Corporation
- History of National Tube Works, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series provides a general introduction to the National Tube Works in McKeesport, Pa. Present in the series are U.S. Steel publications including brochures designed for the public and policy manual books designed for supervisors, as well as job descriptions and documents on topics such as strikes and work stoppages. Box 1 contains rare reports of the industrial relations department of the plant, 1920 to 1921, with tabulation of ethnic origins of workforce and associated social/demographic facts. Box 1 also contains a manuscript history of three early strikes at the Tube Works and a set of photographs taken in and around the plant during the 1936 flood.
  - Early Documents Related to National Tube Works, 1890s-1940s (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Manuals (Box 2)
  - Rosters and Manuals (Box 3)
  - Books and Pamphlets on Management and General Brochures about National Tube Works (Box 4)
    - United States Steel National Plant, National-Duquesne Works, c. 1970; 1.
    - United States Steel Duquesne Plant, National-Duquesne Works, c. 1970; 2.
- Employee Relations, 1930-1985; II.
  The Employee Relations department at National-Duquesne Works covered a variety of concerns surrounding workers' daily lives. This is reflected in the diversity of files within this series. Some documents of interest include employee grievances and minutes of Step 3 meetings, both of which outline the grievance process within U.S. Steel. Compensation, pension, and injury files, as well as National Defense cards, all provide information about employees' nationalities and city residences. Other records in this series illustrate how employees were trained for various jobs around National-Duquesne Works.
  Series arrangement: This series reflects the diversity of actions within the National Works' Employee Relations Department as it was defined in 1980. At that time, the scope of the Employee Relations Department extended to personnel; labor relations; health, hygiene, and safety; and employee benefits. The names of some of the subseries, such as "Pensions, Insurance, and Workman's Compensation" and "Employment, Placement, and Employee Activities," reflect a different organization of departments prior to 1980 and they have been arranged to reflect the 1980 paradigm. In the 1950s, many of these divisions were part of a large Industrial Relations Department.
  - Labor Relations, 1.
    The grievances listed in this subseries are predominantly arranged by their original coding system. It is unknown to us what the letters in the title stand for. The year and case number are separated by a dash. Grievances cover a variety of topics including seniority disputes, wrongful firings, benefits, duty reassessment, and other breaches of union contracts. The Step 3 meeting minutes include information regarding the grievance process used by U.S. Steel and the United Steelworkers of America. Files regarding affirmative action detail how National-Duquesne Works strove to become more of an equal opportunity employer. Matters covered in the subject files include Civil Rights committee meetings, employee complaints, monthly USX and National-Duquesne Works grievance reports, and incentive plans, among others.
    - Grievances: Closed Wage Cases, 1937-1954, 1956-1960 (Box 05-12)
    - Closed Salary Cases, 1942-1950 (Box 13)
    - Closed Job Description and Class Grievances, 1960-1970 (Box 14)
    - Closed Salary Cases, 1962-1970 (Box 15)
    - Closed Grievances, 1962-1964 (Box 16-18)
    - Closed Production & Maintenance Grievances, 1965-1970 (Box 19-23)
    - Salaried and Production & Maintenance National Plant Grievances, 1971-1972 (Box 24-25)
    - Closed Production & Maintenance National Plant Grievances, 1973-1974 (Box 26-27)
    - Closed Grievances, 1975-1982 (Box 28-48)
    - Step 3 Minutes (Wage Grievances), 1937-1950 (Box 49)
    - Step 3 Minutes (Salary Grievances), 1942-1967 (Box 50)
    - Step 3 Minutes (Wage Grievances), 1951-1968 (Box 51-52)
    - Work Stoppages and Strike Files, 1945-1956 (Box 53)
    - Strike and Contract Negotiations, 1959-1964 (Box 54)
    - Affirmative Action Compliance Program, 1970-1979 (Box 55-57)
    - Labor Relations Subject Files (Box 58-63)
    - Employee Relations, 1969-1971 (Box 64)
    - Publicity and Policy, 1960s-1970s (Box 65)
    - Arbitrations (Organized by sections of the contract), 1970-1982 (Box 66-75)
    - Binders: Consent Decree, Savings and Vacation Plan, Local Issues, 1960 (Box 76)
  - Pensions, Insurance, and Workman's Compensation, 2.
    This subseries contains information regarding injured and deceased employees. The compensation files contain plant compensation forms, as well as details of worker injuries and plant hospital treatments. Pension files spanning forty-four years include completed forms, interoffice correspondence, and documents regarding company policy.
    - Individual Compensation Files, 1930-1961 (Box 77-84)
    - Non-inventoried Closed Compensation Cases, 1961 (Box 85)
    - Non-inventoried Closed Compensation Cases, 1962-1964 (Box 86-87)
    - Compensation Cases, 1980-1981 (Box 88)
    - Unemployment Compensation Cards (Box 89)
    - Individual Compensation Case Files and Pension Administration Plan (Box 90)
    - Individual Pension Files of Workers Second Series Deceased, 1931-1946 (Box 91-94)
    - Individual Pension Files of Workers Deceased, 1947-1958 (Box 95-103)
    - Individual Pension Files of Workers Deceased, 1959-1966 (Box 104-114)
    - Individual Pension Files of Workers Deceased, 1968-1975 (Box 115-130)
    - Metropolitan Major Medical, 1966-1969 (Box 131-132)
    - College Recruiting, Pensions, and Vicing, 1950s-1970s (Box 133)
    - Pensions Microfilm
      - U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Pension Files, Deceased and Pensioned, Kakaches-McMillan, 1940s (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 1)
      - U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Pension Files, Deceased and Pensioned, Maisoko-Metrovich, 1940s (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 2)
      - U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Pension Procedures; Memos and Correspondence, Richardson-Davis (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 3)
  - Personnel, 3.
    This subseries contains information pertaining to individual employees. The National Defense Program cards were used for identification of workers and contain such personal data as ethnicity, height, and weight. Many of the cards contain a thumbnail-sized photograph of the employee. Insurance benefit cards and printouts detailing weekly employee benefits are also present.
    - National Defense Cards with Signature Only (Box 134-135)
    - National Defense Cards, 1940s (Box 136-184)
    - Preliminary Data Sheets and National Defense Cards, 1950s (Box 185)
    - National Defense Cards, 1950s (Box 186-188)
    - Employee Rosters (Broadcast Sheets), 1963-1966 (Box 189)
    - Employee Statistics, 1969-1977 (Box 190)
    - Absenteeism at Duquesne and McKeesport, 1980-1982 (Box 191)
    - Plant Labor Pools, 1983-1984 (Box 192)
    - Absenteeism Printouts, 1984 (Box 193)
    - Employment and Income Security and Seniority listings, 1984 (Box 194-195)
    - Sub Register of Benefits, 1984 (Box 196)
    - 20 Year Employees on Layoff or Disability, 1985 (Box 197)
    - Employee List Printouts, 1985 (Box 198)
    - Policies and Printouts, 1980s (Box 199)
    - Miscellaneous Printouts, Lists, and Vacation Eligibility Rosters (Box 200)
    - Employee Records, Monthly Union Check Offs, and Pension Reports (Box 201)
    - Cards of Salaried Workers, Clock S-1235-91796 (Box 202-204)
    - Terminations Card File (Box 205)
    - Rosters concerning Salary and Wages (Box 206)
    - Rosters and Mailing List (Box 207)
    - Pensions Microfilm
      Scope and Contents note
      The microfilm in this section details the career of employees at National-Duquesne Works. Personnel files include basic employee records sheets and changes to employee statistics, such as marital status and address, as well as papers outlining changes to employees' payroll and transfer slips.
      - U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Personnel Services; Contract Admin.; Seniority; Plant Protection, January 1960-September 1971 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 4)
      - U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Personnel Services; Contract Admin.; Plant Protection; Daily Personnel Reports, 1951-1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 5)
      - U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Daily Reports, Personnel, 1956-1961 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 6)
      - U.S. Steel Corp. National Works Daily Reports, Personnel; Local Union Check Offs and Correspondence, 1958-1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 7)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Records), April-June 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 8)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Records), July-October 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 9-10)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Records), October-December 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 11-12)
      - Personnel History Record Cards Inactive Salary and Active Wage Employees, 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 95-96)
      - Personnel History Record Cards Inactive Wage and Salary Terminated Employees, 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 97-98)
      - Chronological File (January-June), January-March 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 13)
      - Chronological File (January-June), March-June 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 14)
      - Chronological File (January-June), June 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 15)
      - Personnel History Record Card IR-109 Active and Inactive, 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 16)
      - Personnel History Record Card IR-109 Inactive (Terminated Employees) Abel-Zolas, 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 17)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), July-August 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 18)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), August-October 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 19)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), October-December 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 20)
      - Miscellaneous, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 21-22)
      - Personnel History Record Card IR-109 Active File-Wage Employees, January 1, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 23-24)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), January-March 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 25)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), April-June 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 26)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), July-December 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 27-29)
      - Personnel History Record Card IR-109 Inactive Files (Terminated Employees) Salary, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 30)
      - Personnel History Record Card IR-109 Active Files, December 31, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 31-35)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), January-February 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 36)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), February-April 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 37)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), April-June 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 38)
      - Personnel History Record Card IR-109 Active and Inactive, 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 39-44)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), July-December 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 45-46)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), January-June 1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 47-48)
      - Personnel History Record Card IR-109 Active File-Wage Employees, 1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 49-50)
      - Miscellaneous, 1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 51)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), July-December 1956 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 52-53)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), January-June 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 54-55)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), July-October 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 5, Reel 56)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), October-December 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 57)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), January- June 1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 58-59)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), January-March 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 60)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), March-June 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 61)
      - Chronological File (supporting documents for Personnel History Record Card IR-109), 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 62)
      - Salary and Wage Terminations, 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6, Reel 63)
  - Health, Hygiene, and Safety, 4.
    This subseries contains a wealth of information regarding the dangers of working at National-Duquesne Works. Accident reports and investigations detail many situations in which the worker's health had failed or those in which the employee was injured while working at the plant. Safety reports and meeting minutes at the plant, regional, and national levels outline ways in which management and supervisors tried to solve safety issues and prevent further injury to workers.
    - Accidents and Injuries
      Section scope note: These records outline the many different types of injuries and accidents that occurred at the National-Duquesne Works. Reports include graphic descriptions of the incidents by the injured worker or witnesses and some include photographs or diagrams of the accident site. Some accident reports even include the nationality of the injured employee.
      - Lost Time Accidents, 1930-1960 (Box 208-212)
      - Injury Reports and Ambulance Calls, 1951-1958 (Box 212)
      - Ambulance Calls, 1960-1962 (Box 213)
      - Delayed Treatment, Serious Minor Injury Cases and Deceased Employees, 1941-1964 (Box 214)
      - Minor Injury Reports, 1955 (Box 215-216)
      - Daily Injury Reports, 1957-1967 (Box Box 217-219)
      - Medical and Pension Records, 1970 (Box 220)
      - Serious Minor Injury Reports, 1958-1963 (Box 221)
      - Safety Department Daily Injury and Hospital Reports, 1959-1962, 1964 (Box 222)
      - Accident Investigations, Daily Injury Slips and Hospital Reports, 1964-1966 (Box 223)
      - Injury Reports, 1961-1963 (Box 224)
      - Consolidated Injury Reports Including Other Plants, 1969-1975 (Box 225)
      - Lost Time Injuries Including Other Plants, 1976-1982 (Box 226-228)
      - US Steel Injuries, 1967-1975 (Box 229)
      - Foreman's Accident Reports, 1981 (Box 230)
      - Statements of Injured Employees, 1964-1968 (Box 231)
      - Outside Contraction, Compensation and Disfigurement Cases, 1969-1979 (Box 232)
    - Safety
      Section scope note: This section includes information on safety meetings and statistics from National-Duquesne Works, U.S. Steel, and various other steel companies. From these documents it can be determined how National-Duquesne Works measured up to other plants in aspects of accidents and safety. Publications intended for workers regarding hygiene and safety are also included, as well as signs posted at the plant.
      - Safety Performances and Minutes of Major Steel Production Companies, 1944-1955 (Box 233)
      - Joint Union Management, Safety and Health Committee Minutes, 1965 (Box 234)
      - Safety Activity Reports, 1970-1974 (Box 235)
      - General Superintendent's Staff Safety Meetings, 1972-1979 (Box 236-237)
      - Safety and Hygiene Pamphlets, 1972-1981 (Box 238)
      - General Superintendents Safety Meetings, 1980-1982 (Box 239)
      - Safety Statistics, 1981-1982 (Box 240)
      - Eastern Steel Works Safety Meeting Minutes and Reports (Box 241)
      - Safety Training and OSHA Files (Box 242)
      - Safety (Box 243-244)
      - Safety Department Binders about Procedure (Box 245)
      - Safety Policy and Reports (Box 246)
      - "Let's better our safety score in '84" Poster, 1983; 1. (Map-case 3, Drawer 12)
      - "Have a safe Merry Christmas" Poster, 1983; 2.
    - Safety Microfilm